Hi, welcome back to the Lam Rim.
And as you can see, we are
starting with the peach tree.
That is the real peach
tree outside of my house.
We planted it this year,
and somehow it grew very
well during the virus time.
We were talking about a famous metaphor
that was written about by Chandrakirti.
He said:
"Love is like the seed for the peach tree.
Love is like the water & the
fertilizer for the peach tree.
Love is like eating the peach."
THOG MTHA' BAR Tim,
THOG MTHA' BAR
In the beginning, in
the end, and in between.
As a seed, as a fruit, and as a tree.
Love is important in all three times.
Then Tsongkhapa was careful to say,
"Look, we are using three
different images of the tree,
of the growth of the tree.
But do not forget we are
talking about one love,
the love is the same.
The examples are three.
The examples are three:
the seed of the tree,
the growing of the tree, and
then the fruit of the tree.
But really, we are just talking
about one love, one single love.
And that is why Chandrakirti
repeats the word love,
love and only love.
Because he wants us to know
that love is the example
in all three metaphors.
All right, so, we are going to the
back to the text of the Lam Rim.
,ZHES GSUNGS PA BZHIN,
THOG MAR THEG CHEN DU
NGES PAR BYED PA DANG,
BYANG CHUB TU SEMS BSKYED
PA'I RTZA BAR GYUR PAS
SA BON LTAR GAL CHE BA,
SA BON LTAR means look, compassion.
SNYING RJE -- karuna -- is like the seed.
Why? He says here,
"Because at the beginning,
it marks you as a
bodhisattva". It marks you.
It is what marks you in the
beginning as a bodhisattva.
It is like you have a sign
on your head or something.
If you have this kind of compassion.
I think it is nice to,
when you talk about compassion
in the seven-step cause and
effect bodhichitta training,
I think it is good if you
talk about compassion.
You think about pain, shared, shared pain.
I think compassion means
that you empathize with other people.
Compassion always implies
that you have had some pain yourself.
Then when you see other people having it,
you feel compassion.
So I think compassion
is sort of an experience
of sharing pain in this world.
This world is painful for everybody.
The biggest people to the smallest people
have the same pain. And
it is a shared experience.
It is something that
brings us all together.
It should bring us together.
I think, we get into pain
and we get grumpy. Then
we fight with each other.
But really we are all
experiencing the same pain.
We are all falling down
in the same airplane.
I think pain should bring us together.
We should think, "I am
having pain today in my foot
and everyone else around me
is having some kind of pain."
It should make us softer
to each other, I think.
So, he says at the beginning,
this kind of compassion,
it marks you as a bodhisattva.
It is the, ultimately, this
kind of empathy where you think,
"I am having the same
pain as you are having,"
is what is going to take us to
the vision of a bodhisattva.
Eventually, that kind of thinking
that everybody around me has
some kind of pain going on,
that kind of thinking
is what is going to
make you a bodhisattva.
So, it is not very hard.
It is not very difficult to acknowledge
that everyone around us
is having the same kind of
problems that we are having.
Today was my foot, or somebody else.
It is not a big logical leap
to understand that everyone
has something going on.
Then that is a very powerful
seed, says Chandrakirti,
that is a powerful seed for bodhichitta.
BAR DU in the next paragraph.
RGYAL SRAS KYI SPYOD PAR
MI ZHUM PA'I GO CHA'I
BRTZON 'GRUS SKYED PAS
CHU LUD LTAR GAL CHE BA
So, that is at the beginning,
and now in the interim, during our work
on the spiritual path, this
compassion is like water.
Or he says here LUD
which means fertilizer,
like water or fertilizer on the tree.
Why? Because if you have
that kind of shared suffering,
feeling we are in this together,
if you have this kind of attitude,
that we are all in this pain together,
that is a kind of GO CHA.
What is GO CHA, you guys remember?
Varma? Varman?
Armor, knight's armor, the
steel coat that you put on.
So, after you get on the spiritual path,
this awareness that we
are all having problems.
We are all suffering pretty
equally. It is like armor.
Armor means for your BRTZON 'GRUS.
BRTZON 'GRUS means
when you do your Buddhist practice,
you do it in a good mood.
You are not like a grumpy bodhisattva.
You are like, "Yeah, we
are all having trouble,
and okay, what the heck?
Come on, let us do something
good with our lives.
Let us do something beautiful together."
So, it is a kind of BRTZON 'GRUS
that compassion or that
empathy with other people,
where we are all aware
that we all have problems.
It is hard to say whose
problems are worse.
We all have problems.
And keeping that in mind is like an armor
or a shield that protects your joy.
It protects your joy with your practice.
Then you do not get too serious.
You do not get grumpy.
You are like, "Okay, I can do this."
And it protects you from
breakdowns, practice breakdowns.
By the way, if you never
had a practice breakdown,
it is because you are not practicing.
So, Grandpa has a practice
breakdown every two days.
If you do not have a practice breakdown,
I think you are not a
human being, or something.
We all mess up. We all
have practice breakdown.
But if you remember,
that we are all suffering
pretty much the same,
then your practice
breakdowns will be shorter
and you will come back
to your practice quicker.
But by the way, if you have
a breakdown in your practice,
you get depressed, you
do something terrible
that you thought you would not do again,
then just get back up%
and think, "Everyone is messed up.
We are all messed up equally.
Come on, let us get back on the horse
and let us keep going."
All right, so, that is
beginning and interim.
THA MAR means, in the next paragraph,
THA MAR SANGS RGYAS THOB NAS KYANG
It is very interesting
that even after you achieve enlightenment,
you reach Buddhahood,
so yeah, you should not need
the steps to get
bodhichitta anymore, right?
Like, if you reached Buddhahood,
maybe you outgrew six of the seven steps.
It makes sense.
I already reached the bodhisattva.
So I do not need the
first six steps anymore.
And Chandrakirti says,
"Uh-uh, no, no, no, no, no.
Do not think like that."
Buddhas enjoy peach fruits.
Buddhas enjoy their enlightenment.
Buddhas enjoy the feeling
of shared empathy also.
They do not give it up
after they become a Buddha.
When you become a full bodhisattva,
when you finally reach bodhichitta,
which is that vision of a bodhisattva,
when you finally reach that,
it is not like you outgrow compassion.
Compassion then becomes
some kind of delicious fruit
that you can keep eating forever,
for billions of lives, forever.
So it is not like you outgrow it.
You need it as a seed for
your bodhisattva practice.
You need it to protect your joy
while you are a bodhisattva.
And then you are going
to sit and chew on it
after you become a Buddha,
and just enjoy the
feeling of shared empathy.
All right, we are going to
go onto the next topic here.
BYANG CHUB KYI SEMS
SHUGS DRAG LOD KYANG 'DI'I RJES SU 'GRO
This feeling of shared suffering
is going to determine the DRAG LOD
in the middle of the next line. DRAG LOD.
That feeling of shared suffering
is what is going to decide the DRAG LOD
of your bodhichitta.
DRAG LOD means
if you are playing a guitar
you stretch the string very tight,
that is called DRAG.
And then you loosen the string,
it is called LOD, okay?
So DRAG LOD means
how tight is the string on your guitar.
It is called DRAG LOD.
What does it mean with bodhichitta?
Whether your vision of the
future of jumping across planets
is strong or kind of floppy,
is determined by your compassion.
So, the compassion is the hand
which is tightening the string.
And if your shared feeling of suffering
is strong,
then your bodhichitta is tight
and makes a beautiful sound.
If your compassion is lazy, and
you do not think about how we
are all suffering together,
then it is going to be
your bodhichitta will
also be kind of sloppy
and loose. Boing, boing.
BYANG SEMS RNAMS KYANG SA
LAM BGROD TSUL MYUR BUL
So MYUR BUL is a parallel
to DRAG LOD.
DRAG LOD means how tight is the string?
MYUR BUL means how fast is the progress?
How fast does the car go?
Here we have a picture of a car.
I do not know, when I was a teenager,
this was heaven to get a car.
The day I met Veronica, I was
under a race car, fixing it.
I saw her feet first.
And so for, I don´t know,
for an Arizona boy, a
fast car is like heaven.
How fast is your bodhichitta?
How fast are you going to travel the path?
SA LAM
How fast are you going to
go through the five paths?
How fast are you going to go
through the ten bodhisattva levels?
It all depends on how
strong is your feeling
that we are all going
down in the same airplane.
We are all in the same boat.
SNA TSOGS 'BYUNG BA'I RTZA
BA SNYING RJE SHUGS CHE CHUNG
LAS BYUNG
He has three pairs of words here.
He has: DRAG LOD - MYUR BUL - CHE CHUNG
DRAG LOD - MYUR BUL - CHE CHUNG
The tightness of your compassion
determines your bodhichitta.
The speed that you are going to go,
MYUR BUL, fast or slow,
is determined by your compassion
and SHUGS CHE CHUNG
means big or small power.
Vega
SHUGS to your shared feeling of pain,
sharing pain with others.
All right, that is how it
makes your car go faster.
All right, next paragraph.
BYANG CHUB SEMS DPA' SNGAGS LA ZHUGS NAS
MYUR LAM 'TSOL ZHING,
Then he says a very interesting thing,
he is like, "Look, everybody knows
that if you really want to help people,
you should practice the Diamond Way,
the secret teachings, okay?
If you really want to help people,
then you should practice the Diamond Way,
or the secret teachings.
Why? Because it is faster.
You can reach enlightenment
in one lifetime instead of
a few billion lifetimes,
if you practice Diamond Way.
Then he challenges us, very interesting.
Pabongka says, "Hey, do
you want to take a guess?
Why it is faster?
Do you want to guess why it is faster."
And then you are supposed to say,
"I know from what you just said,"
Tantra must be faster
because you have more compassion.
Maybe that is why secret
teachings work faster.
Maybe if you dial up your
compassion to much higher level,
that is what makes Diamond Way faster.
BGROD PA SHIN TU MYUR BA
YANG SNYING RJE'I STOBS
SNYING RJE'I STOBS it is
the power of compassion
that makes Tantra faster.
You dial up your feeling that
we are suffering together.
Then you can, then you
did enter the Diamond Way.
BU ME DONG DU LHUNG NA
DE'I PHA MAS MYUR DU 'DON
We are having fun in Sedona
because people keep having babies.
Luckily it is not me, but
Nick and Erin had a baby.
Adam and Katey had a baby.
Then Nour and Seiji had a baby.
And if you met Maitri, I don´t know,
probably you have seen his pictures.
But, if you did not see his
pictures, you got them, Tim?
I will send you one. There;s a new one.
That is how you can
tell I am a real Grandpa
because I actually look at
all the pictures they send me.
You want the serious
one or the sleepy one?
- Which ever one is the cutest one
and where people like go, "Aww."
- Cute, you want cute, oh,
I am going to send you cute.
Okay Tim is going to display it.
Let´s see, hmm.
Where is Tim? Okay.
Okay, by the way, I am
not just wasting time,
this is a purpose.
I sent it to your phone, I think.
If you have a new baby, like
Nour and Seiji have a new baby,
and if that baby fell into a barbecue,
if that cute, little baby
fell into a barbecue.
LHUNG NA
then if we are all standing
there, me, Tim, Christina,
and we are watching the baby
fall into the barbecue, then...
There is Maitri from a few days ago, okay?
If the baby fell into a barbecue,
who is going to move first?
- Mom.
- Yeah, Nour,
Yeah, Nour and Seiji,
They are going to move a
millisecond before the rest of us.
Not because we are not compassionate,
we are nice people.
But we do not love the baby like they do.
They are going to move instantaneously.
They are going to move.
And then we are going to go,
"Oh, let´s do something."
We are going to be behind the parents.
They are going to jump right away.
So, that is called here
PHA MAS MYUR DU 'DON.
The mom and dad will act quickly.
NYE 'BREL GYIS, grandpa, uncle, aunt,
here's the picture. You
can see the picture here,
uncle and aunt. They are
going to move slower.
Grandpa Mike.
I think the parents are
sitting at the end of the table
and the uncle and aunt
are on the left side.
If that girl on the right,
if suddenly she drops her
knife and stabs herself,
the parents are going to move first.
Then later, the uncle and
aunt will do something,
a second later, but the
parents will move first.
NYE 'BREL GYIS DE MA THAG 'DON MI NUS PA
So, NYE 'BREL means relatives:
uncle, aunt, cousin, friend, grandpa,
are not going to move as fast.
It is the mother and
father who move first.
LTA BU'I SNYING RJE'I SHUGS
DRAG ZHAN GYIS BYUNG BA YIN,
How fast you move is SHUGS DRAG.
Sorry, DRAG ZHAN.
DRAG means powerful.
It is used for fierce deities.
DRAG PA
And then ZHAN PA means watered down,
weak, ZHAN PA means weak.
So whether your compassion
is like, [grunts]
like a tiger, or whether your compassion
is like, I do not know, some sleepy guy,
that is going to decide
how fast you can go.
How fast you move.
SNYING RJE 'DI BSGOM PA NA
THOG MAR BSHAN PAS GSOD BZHIN
PA'I LUG LTA BU LA DMIGS NAS
If you have a problem that
you have weakling compassion.
If you are compassionate is wimpy,
your compassion is not strong,
your compassion is like,
like some lazy guy. If
you have that problem,
that is called BSHAN PA.
If your compassion
is a little bit BSHAN PAS,
Pabongka says, "I have
a suggestion for you.
I have a cure for wimpy."
What is another word for wimpy?
I don't know, half-ass,
half-assed compassion.
"If you have half-assed compassion,
then I have a suggestion for you.
I have something you can do."
What? Meditate on, you got a
picture for me, Seiji?, sorry.
I keep calling Pachi
Seiji, I do not know why.
It is because you both end
in an "I", or something.
- [Man] I have a picture of some-
- Yeah, this is a real photo.
I found it on the internet.
This sheep, when they
mark it with the paint,
it means kill this sheep
today, killed this one today.
The paint on the back of the sheep,
means kill this one today.
All these baby sheep are
going to become veal.
What do you call that in Austria?
Some kind of special dish there.
- [Woman] Wiener schnitzel.
- [Michael] Hmm?
- [Woman] Wiener schnitzel?
- I guess it is Wiener
schnitzel, I do not know.
Anyway, they have to kill a baby sheep
to get it, to make it.
This picture is amazing
because they put all
the mothers on one side,
they put all the baby
sheep on the other side.
And they are going to kill the baby sheep.
This baby sheep is trying to get
over the fence back to his mom.
So, he senses that he
is going to be killed
in the next few minutes.
And he is struggling to get
over the fence to his mom.
Probably his mom is trying
to help him get back in.
So, he says, Pabongka says,
"If you have trouble feeling compassion,
if you are kind of cold-hearted,
or maybe you are just too
busy to feel compassion,
Then he says, "Close your eyes.
Imagine a sheep. Imagine
that sheep, real sheep."
I am sure it was killed in the
next few minutes, by the way.
Someone has gotten a big knife
they are holding the sheep down
on the ground, upside down."
Here it means GNAM SA MGO MJUG,
means... What do you call it in Chinese?
天 (Tiān)
How do you say earth
and sky? 望天（Wàng Tiān）
Earth and sky are reverse for him.
It means he is on his back
and the sky is the ground,
and the ground is the sky
for him. It is on his back,
the world has topsy-turny.
The world is reversed for him.
MJUG LDOG PA LTAR GAN RKYAL DU BSGYEL,
He is flopped down, face up on his back.
YAN LAG NI THA GUS GCINGS,
And then they tie his arms down.
They tie the sheep's arms down.
SHED RGYAGS KYANG MI THUB,
No hope of escape.
SROG LA BAB PAR NI MNGON SUM DU SHES,
The sheep is not stupid.
The sheep knows MNGON SUM DU
as opposed to RJES DPAG.
He knows directly.
It is not logic. He is not using logic,
"Maybe I am going to get killed."
He knows. He is not stupid.
MNGON SUM means he has a direct insight
into the next five minutes.
He knows he is going to die.
BROS PAS NI MI THAR
He cannot run away. He knows
he has no hope of escaping.
MGON DANG SKYABS MED PAR
And he knows Superman
is not going to show up
in the next two minutes.
He knows there is no sheep
Superman going to show up
and let him go. He knows that.
MIG MCHI MA TZA RER
He starts to cry. Animals start to cry
when they are about to die,
they know. And tears come in their eyes.
BSHAN PA'I GDONG DU RIG RIG TU BLTA
BSHAN PA means the butcher,
the guy with the knife,
they are looking up in the butcher's face,
the human's face.
RIG RIG
means they know, they know.
They know what is going on.
They know what is happening.
BLTA BZHIN 'JIGS SKRAG
They are terrified. They
are totally terrified
for their life.
SDUG BSNGAL MI BZAD PA'I NGANG NAS
Then in this state of total terror,
they are killed. They lose their life.
Their life is given in
a state of total terror
about what is happening.
They know what is happening.
The terror does not stop it.
Then the knife comes down and they die.
GSOD LUGS NGAN PA SNA
TSOGS ZHIG GIS 'CHI LUGS
There are lots of ways to kill animals.
If that one does not work for you,
you can do the one about cattle.
Get a hook, put in their leg.
Then they are upside down.
They are upside down. They are like this.
And then the guy [cutting motion].
I have a friend in Argentina
and her husband is a butcher
in a slaughter house.
He said they all have mental problems,
all of the guys with the knife.
They start to develop
serious mental problems
because all day long,
they have to kill the
animals, covered with blood.
RANG RES
So if you have trouble feeling empathy,
then just think about the
baby sheep in the picture.
All right, lamb, right?
RANG RES DE LTAR GSOD PAR MTHONG BA NA
Then you and me,
we are so hardhearted
that when we see a movie
or there are movies made
by vegetarian groups,
you can see these movies.
Then we think, LUG DES CANG BSAM AE SHES
AE SHES it is means,
you know, I don´t think
they really feel anything,
they are just animals.
I hear this argument a lot.
You probably heard this argument a lot.
I do not have to be vegetarian. Why?
We can kill animals.
Some people say the Bible
says that. I think it is BS.
Animals belong to man.
Man can kill animals.
Animals do not feel anything.
Well then why do Americans
spend $3 billion a year
to make their pets happy if
pets can not feel anything.
The same people who say
you can kill an animal
and they do not feel anything,
spend $3 billion a year
making their pets happy.
This is a contradiction there.
Some kind of contradiction there.
Of course, they understand.
That is why you pet a dog
because it makes them happy, duh.
My ballet teacher used
to say, "Duh, duh, duh."
CANG BSAM AE SHES NA SNYAM YANG
means I know some of you guys are thinking
that animals do not really
know what is going on
and they just die
without feeling anything.
SNGON BSHAN PA
"But I will tell you a story," he says,
"I will tell you a story.
I will prove to you that you are wrong.
Do not tell me that they do
not know what is going on."
SNGON BSHAN PA ZHIG GIS
There was a time recently in the past.
There was a butcher killing some sheep.
LUG MANG PO GSOD SKABS,
He had a big group of sheep
and he was killing them one by one.
SNGA MA 'GA' BSAD ZIN NAS,
A few had gone before,
a few were already dead.
BSAD ZIN NAS - ZIN means
past tense, right Tim?
He had killed a couple already.
GCIG GSOD RGYUR THAG PAS
When he was grabbing another
to kill the next one,
BAR DER,
during the time when he is distracted,
and trying to grab the
next sheep to kill him,
he set his knife down on the ground.
BAR DER, BSHAN PA'I GRI DE LUG
GCIG GI NYE 'GRAM NA YOD PA
And there was another
sheep next to the knife.
LUG DES GRI DE LA LAG PAS SA BKAB STE
Then the other sheep was trying
to push dirt over the knife
to hide the knife so the
butcher would not find it.
So, the second sheep was like,
I guess he was super smart,
and he was trying to
cover the knife with dirt,
BKAB STE
SBA BA means try to hide it.
SBA BA'I TSUL BYAS BA'I RABS
This RABS means...
This is the RABS in SKYES RABS
which is Jataka,
which means tales of birth.
So this RABS means
a tale or story.
RABS LTAR 'JIGS SKRAG DANG
SDUG BSNGAL BZOD DKA' BA YOD,
BZOD DKA' BA means unbearable.
These animals, don´t think
they don´t have feelings,
of course they have feelings.
That is why you pet a dog.
That is why you pet a
cat. They have feelings.
And so you can decide to eat meat.
You can decide to kill these animals.
You are just as much the
killer if you eat meat
than if you stab them.
It is the same thing.
When you eat meat, you
are stabbing this sheep.
You are not different from
the butcher. You are the same.
In fact, you are worse because
you are paying the butcher.
So you are making double karma.
So you can say, "I am going
to eat meat anyway, Geshe-la".
But do not tell me they can not feel it.
That is just bullshit.
Of course, they can feel
it. And nobody wants to die.
That is why birds run away
when you come outside because
they do not want to die.
It is not that they do not like you.
They are afraid of you.
Birds are smart. They
learned a million years ago
to run away from humans.
I have one bird in a thousand in my house.
He will sit and wait for
me to bring the food.
But I think I am afraid he
might not live very long.
DE LTAR CI DRAG LA THUG
PA DE BZHIN DU DA LTA
GSOD SAR MA SLEBS PAR,
Now Pabongka Rinpoche takes it
in a very interesting direction.
He says, "CI DRAG LA THUG PA."
We can talk about the
desperate last minutes
of animals and people who are dying.
We can talk about the last few minutes
after you get hit by a car.
We can talk about the last
few minutes in the hospital
with cancer. We can talk
about the last few minutes.
You got the feeling, right?
But now I want you to consider,
RI LA RTZVA KHAR 'GRIM PA'I LUG
now I want you to consider a nice
healthy young sheep in his or her prime,
chewing grass contentedly
on top of the mountain.
Let us not talk about a sheep
who is in the hand of the butcher.
Let´s talk about those
beautiful months and years
that those sheep spent grazing
in this bucolic pastures
with nice green grass and
happily eating the grass.
Come on, what is the difference?
In the hand of the butcher
or chewing your green grass
on the way to the hand of the butcher?
What is the difference?
Pabongka is like, "What
is the difference?"
If you are going to have
compassion for a sheep
while the knife is going into his neck,
can´t you have compassion
for the sheep on the mountain
chewing the nice green grass
when he is young and healthy?
Don´t you see it is no different?
SNGA PHYI'I KHYAD TZAM LAS
It is just a difference in timing.
The situation is the same.
Their situation is the same.
The timing is different.
One is chewing, one is dying.
But they are both dying, aren't they?
And isn't it true of everybody,
everybody around you is dying.
So try to feel some compassion,
meaning, try to feel some
group suffering, joy.
We are all together in this.
And some of us are chewing grass,
and some of us are in the
hospital this morning.
But aren't we all in
the same place, really?
TZAM LAS DE DANG KHYAD
PAR MED PA ZHIG 'ONG,
Then you will come to a point
where you see that the
people chewing the grass,
here are people chewing the grass
at the Black Hole Cafe.
Yes, come on, you have my Black Hole.
This is my Black Hole Cafe.
Why is it called Black Hole Cafe?
I bought this cafe.
When money comes near the cafe,
it disappears like a black hole.
The expenses are unbelievable.
Actually the guy who owned it before
was a famous astronomer.
You can see some black
holes in the pictures.
Those are his pictures of black holes.
I thought maybe we should keep
those pictures in the cafe
because the money seems to go
into a black hole in that cafe.
Why am I showing this picture?
Who is going to make $100 this morning?
We got like seven or eight
veteran dharma students here.
Why am I showing the Peach Tree Cafe?
[Woman speaks Indistinctly]
Yes, okay, 50 bucks for Gyelse,
50 bucks for Tim.
- [Man] Understand that
they are eating....
- Yes, those guys having
the signature cinnamon rolls
in the Peach Tree Cafe.
By the way, if you ever come to America,
you have to go there
and eat a cinnamon roll.
Those guys sitting there
quietly enjoying Grandpa's breakfast,
they are the same as the people
in the hospital this
morning dying of cancer.
They are the same.
The people right now
whose head is going through
the windshield in their car,
right now, somewhere, right?
Their head is smashing through
the windshield of their car.
Two minutes ago they were texting
with their husband about
breakfast and now they are dying.
In this moment they are dying.
Those people who are dying
in a car accident right now
and the people sitting in Grandpa's cafe
having a wonderful
breakfast, they are the same.
It is all the same.
Try to understand this.
They are in the same
airplane, falling down.
KHYAD TZAM LAS DE DANG KHYAD PAR MED
ZHIG 'ONG means there will be a day
when you will understand that
the person sitting in the cafe
having a high quality,
well-priced breakfast
and a person dying in a car accident
right at this moment
somewhere, they are the same.
They are not different.
So, try to have some
love for people, come on.
We are all having a car
accident this morning.
All right. DE DAG TSE RABS
SNGA MA'I RANG GI MA BYAS
TSUL BSAMS NAS
And that person who is
sitting in the cafe dying
has been your mom.
Don´t forget what we are talking
about. They were your mom.
They took care of you.
SNYING RJE BSGOM
Then finally you can SNYING RJE BSGOM.
Finally, that is a compassion meditation.
Look at the people. Go to a nice cafe.
We are going to take everybody
to a cafe this morning
because it is our last filming day.
You guys go to a cafe
on your own, okay, Rob?
But we are going to sit
with a bunch of dying people
and have a cinnamon roll
together, or coffee.
So, SNYING RJE BSGOM.
You do not need to sit
on a meditation cushion
to meditate on compassion,
you can go out to a cafe
and look at the people,
including yourself.
DE LA MYONG BA SKYES PA NA
And this is a beautiful word,
MYONG BA SKYES PA NA means
if you get good at this,
if you get good at this, if
you get good at doing this
in a cafe, SNGAR RANG STENG
DU BSGOMS PA'I NGAN SONG GI
SDUG BSNGAL RNAMS BSAMS TE
I will give you a clue
how to make it more intense.
I will give you a clue,
We spent ten years going through
the two lower sections of the Lam Rim.
You and me spent ten years
going through the steps
for people who have lesser motivation
and steps of people for medium motivation.
We spent ten years on that.
We struggled through all the hell realms,
the animal realms, the preta realms,
the suffering of the humans.
Come on, we did it for years.
RANG STENG DU BSGOMS PA'I
RANG STENG DU
But those contemplations in
the lower parts of the Lam Rim
were focused on me.
I have been into hell. I was an animal.
I was a hungry ghost.
They are all focused on me.
Now take that as a foundation,
take that as a foundation
and expand it to other people. That's all.
So, he is calling on your
ten years of Lam Rim.
He says, "Look, don´t waste the tem years
you just spent to get here.
Don´t forget the steps for
people of lower motivation
are like the first bricks of a wall
and they support the
later bricks of the wall."
So use the meditations
you did for ten years
and now expand them to
everybody in the cafe.
SEMS CAN GZHAN RNAMS KYANG DE
LTAR SDUG BSNGAL MYONG DANG
MYONG BZHIN PA RNAMS BSGOMS NAS,
You can meditate about how
much suffering people have had
and how much suffering
people are having right now
in hospitals, in car
accidents, all over the world.
All right, new paragraph.
AA MA DE DAG 'GA' ZHIG NI
DMYAL BAR LCAGS SREG TU BSREG
Right now, forget the car accident.
Some of your mothers
are in the hell realms
in a country made of
iron and it's red hot.
They are living in a whole
continent made of iron
and it is red hot,
and no matter where they
run, they are burned.
The whole continent is red
hot iron, like a frying pan.
And your moms, right now,
are running across that steel hopelessly.
There is no hope for them.
They can not go anywhere.
They just have to keep running.
KHRO CHUR 'TSOD,
Some of them are being dipped
in molten steel as we speak.
Some of the people who have been your mom
are being dipped in
molten steel right now.
ZHIG NI YI DVAGS SU SKYES NAS
Some of them are spirits in this realm.
They are running here and there
to get a piece of spit or a piece of shit.
They are hungry ghosts.
They are trying to eat
something, anything.
They do not have the karma to see anything
except a little bit of it pee pee,
or something like that.
GDUNG BA SOGS BSAMS NAS SNYING RJE BSKYED
So try to expand your feeling
that we are all in the same
airplane, falling down.
Try to expand that feeling
to all the beings in other realms.
And I have a picture here.
I was trying to find a
picture of a frying pan.
I could not very well.
I have a picture.
It is kind of like a barbecue.
If you had to think about the hell realms,
and you say, "Geshe-la, but
that's just a chicken leg."
No, but all the parts of the hell beings,
they look the same.
Probably if you went there,
you would think somebody
was cooking chicken,
but those are people. That
is how it feels there.
Let us go a little bit more.
DE LA SNYING RJE SKYES PA NA,
If you can manage to feel
some kind of shared sense
of suffering with those beings
running across the hot metal
in the hell realms. DPER
NA, RI LA YOD PA'I LUG DANG
GSOD BZHIN PA'I LUG GNYIS
And then you can close your eyes
and think of RI LA YOD PA'I LUG
the sheep standing on the mountain,
eating some grass happily.
GSOD BZHIN PA'I LUG
The sheep with the knife
halfway through his throat.
GSOD PA SNGA PHYI TZAM LAS KHYAD MED
There is just a difference of timing.
There is not a difference of
reality. They are both dying.
They both have the knife in their throat.
DA LTA MI YUL NA SDIG PA BYED PAR
Then he goes to a very
interesting example.
Do you have that picture for me, Pachi?
Where is that picture?
The website I use for my
pictures is a business,
it is a business website I use it for DCI.
I pay a lot of money every month.
And you can find 10,000 pictures
of successful young people
because that's the dream.
That is the American dream.
That is the world dream.
These amazing smart young people,
they are about to have their first baby.
They are negotiating their
first house right now.
He drove to the real estate
agent in his new Tesla.
You look at those people and you say,
"Guys, at least someone is doing okay.
At least someone is having a good life."
They are in love. That guy
looks like he has big muscles.
She is cute. He has hair on his head.
They are buying a new house.
At least somebody is having a good life.
Maybe my life is kind of
difficult and dull, but thank God
there are some smart,
healthy, rich, young people.
It makes me happy to see.
Yes, and he says again,
SDIG PA BYED PAR PHO SKYEN MDOG
means yeah, they look okay,
they look fine, but they are suffering
the second kind of suffering.
They are suffering the
second kind of suffering.
SDUG BSNGAL DANG SDUG BSNGAL GYI RGYU
For $100
Suddenly, Tim woke up. His eyes...
- [Woman] Suffering of suffering.
- No.
- [Women] Suffering in pain.
SDUG BSNGAL DANG SDUG BSNGAL GYI RGYU
- Come on, come on.
- [Man] Suffering...
- Yeah, cancel that bet.
This is the second kind
of invisible suffering
where people are collecting the causes
for later suffering.
PHO SKYEN MDOG means they look successful,
young, bright, happy. And they got there
by ignoring poor people in
Africa, by buying stocks
in the petroleum companies
that poison the earth.
In Arizona, they drove to the
real estate agent in a truck
that would hold forty people
because they want a new truck.
They are just burning the world's oil.
They are killing the world
by having this big truck for one person.
And they are sheep on the mountain
because they are swimming
in the cause of suffering.
They are swimming in
the cause of suffering.
Are those two young people suffering?
Yes. Why?
They are are swimming in
the causes of suffering.
All of this consumption
that they are collecting
is hurting people.
Most of the consumption
that they are enjoying
because they are young, and smart,
and they can make more money for awhile.
It is hurting other people.
BYED PAR
SKYEN MDOG KHA BA means
"Yeah, they look fine, but,"
RNAMS KYANG NGAN SONG DU
LTUNG BAR NGES
Definitely, they are collecting causes
SDUG BSNGAL GYI RGYU
which will take them to the lower realms.
They are ignoring this planet.
They are ignoring the poor
people on this planet.
They are ignoring the elderly, the sick.
They are having fun and then
they are collecting causes.
There are the sheep on the mountain.
NGAN SONG DU LTUNG BAR NGES
PAS DA LTA LHUNG ZIN PA
RNAMS DANG KHYAD MED TSUL
They are no different
if they are collecting
causes to be a hungry ghost.
They are no different from
a hungry ghost, really.
They are the same.
Try to understand it's the same.
Basically, we are all
messing up all the time,
not just rich, young yuppies.
We are all messing up all the time.
We are all using cars that
we do not really need.
And yes, we are swimming in
the causes of future suffering.
DE NAS TSE 'DI'I AA MAS
KYANG SDUG BSNGAL GYI RGYU
LA LONGS SPYOD PA LA SNYING RJE BSGOM
Of course, you should have compassion
if your mother in this life was engaging
in the causes of future suffering.
If she was having fun, but
causing future pain for herself,
like over eating, is a perfect example.
It is SDUG BSNGAL GYI RGYU,
but it is not SDUG BSNGAL.
It is the cause for future
suffering, diabetes,
heart problems, but it
is not suffering yet.
LONGS SPYOD PA LA SNYING RJE BSGOM
Try to have compassion also
for people who look like
they are doing okay,
but they are really just collecting
the causes for future suffering.
DE NAS GNYEN 'BREL SOGS
GZHAN RNAMS KYIS KYANG TSE
'DI'I SO TSIS SDIG LTUNG KHO NA LA BRTZON
Then try to expand it from your
mom to your other relatives.
There is a word here called SO TSIS
SO TSIS means all the effort
and the subtle bad deeds you
do to have a better life.
In America, they call better life.
You have a bigger house.
You have a nicer car.
You have nicer clothes. The
effort to get a bigger house,
bigger car, nicer clothes,
oftentimes, not always, can
involve cheating other people,
hurting other people,
ignoring other people.
And so you are just collecting bad deeds.
BRTZON ZHING
SO TSIS means,
in America, they call it the
good life, or better life.
There is another word.
The good life. The good life.
All right, and we have, yes,
there is a picture here.
Do you got one?
I think it is a businesswoman
and a businessman.
Next picture.
There we go!
Yes, I feel like this guy
is cheating the lady,
and she knows it.
I mean, normally, if you have
been in business for awhile,
you can smell it when someone
is trying to cheat you.
And he is like, "Just sign."
She is like, "Well, I do not think so."
She's thinking about,
she's having compassion
for him because he is a nice guy.
He is trying to make more money
and he is telling some
small lies. That is all.
She is seeing his future.
Wow, this is a long class.
One more, one more.
DA LTA MTHO RIS KYI GNAS SKABS
NA'ANG SDUG BSNGAL GSUM GYIS
MNAR BZHIN DU,
Look, even if you are in the higher realms
and you made it to the human realm,
you still have the three
kinds of suffering, right?
Suffering is suffering: backaches.
Suffering of change; a nice
breakfast at a cafe, brunch.
And suffering of general
old age and death,
which is going on all the time
as the background of the
other two sufferings.
GSUM GYIS MNAR BZHIN DU, DA
DUNG DE LAS CHES CHE BA'I
NGAN 'GRO'I SDUG BSNGAL MYONG 'GYUR GYI
RGYU LA BRTZON PA DANG,
People, like that young couple,
they also are experiencing
the three sufferings all the time.
On top of that, they are engaging in,
I would say wasteful behavior,
hurting the environment
and collecting the causes
to suffer more in the future.
So they are having a good
life. It is still marred
by the three sufferings, and
they are collecting causes
for a really bad middle-age,
which we know. We have seen it. All right.
DER MA ZAD, SEMS CAN THAMS
CAD KYANG SDUG BSNGAL DANG
SDUG BSNGAL GYI RGYU LA
SPYAD SPYAD PA YIN PAS
And all other living beings are the same.
They have three sufferings
going on all the time,
at all ages of life.
Then everybody around us, including us,
we are creating seeds
which will cause us more
trouble in the future. YIN PAS
AA MA DRIN CAN 'DI DAG SDUG
BSNGAL DANG SDUG BSNGAL GYI RGYU
DANG BRAL NA CI MA RUNG,
And here comes the formula
for the Immeasurables.
And this one is Immeasurable
compassion, right?
SDUG BSNGAL GYI RGYU
DANG BRAL NA CI MA RUNG
How nice it would be if even
this bright young couple
did not have the three kinds of suffering
going on all the time and they
were not hurting the world
and collecting causes
for future suffering?
Wouldn't that be nice?
CI MA RUNG -- Wouldn't that be nice?
DE DAG GYUR CIG
He is missing one here.
DE DAG GYUR CIG means they should,
they should be, they should
be free from those sufferings.
DE LTAR BDAG GIS BYA'O,
what does that mean?
BDAG GIS BYA'O
I will do it.
I will make sure they
get out of those trouble.
And that is SNYING RJE CHEN PO.
That is Maha Karuṇa.
That is great compassion.
We are going to go on next class
to LHAG BSAM,
which means what? LHAG BSAM
Personal responsibility.
And we finished compassion.
Yay, you graduated from compassion.
See your next class. Yay!